Guide to the New York University Archives Collection of NYU Presidential Portraits MC.376
New York University Archives
New York University Archives Collection of NYU Presidential Portraits
circa 1831-2023
New York University Archives
New York University
MC.376
57.75 linear feet in 16 portraits
From 1831-2023, 16 men have acted as the Chancellor or President of New York University. The New York University Archives Collection of NYU Presidential Portraits consists of portraits representing people who have held this title.
Scope and Contents
The New York University Archives Collection of NYU Presidential Portraits (dated circa 1831-2023) consists of 16 portraits representing people who have held the title of Chancellor or President of NYU.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically by presidential term.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Many of the portraits were commissioned by the University; they were stored and displayed in various locations across campus, most recently in the Mamdouha S. Bobst Gallery in Bobst Library. They were transferred to the NYU Archives in February 2023. The accession number associated with this transfer is 2023.009.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Originals are not available due to fragility and exhibition; use photographed copies.
Historical Note
From 1831-2023, 16 men have acted as the Chancellor or President of New York University. Beginning in 1831, the top-ranking office was titled Chancellor. In 1956, the Office of the President was created as the chief administrative post.
Accruals
Further accurals to this collection are expected.
Universities and colleges.; Universities and Colleges -- Administration; Education, Higher -- New York (N.Y.); College Presidents -- New York (State); Portraits.; New York University
- James M. Mathews, circa early 1800s; cuid18138; This portrait measures approximately 10' x 5'. (Item mc_376_cuid18138)
  Biographical / Historical
  James M. Mathews was the first Chancellor of NYU, serving from 1831-1839.
  Scope and Contents
  This portrait was painted by Cephas Giovanni Thompson sometime in the early 19th century.
- Theodore Frelinghuysen, circa early 1800s; cuid18139; This portrait measures approximately 10' x 5'. (Item mc_376_cuid18139)
  Theodore Frelinghuysen was the second Chancellor of NYU, serving from 1839-1850.
  The painter of this portrait is unknown.
- Isaac Ferris, 1861; cuid18140; This portrait measures approximately 10' x 5'. (Item mc_376_cuid18140)
  Isaac Ferris was the third Chancellor of NYU, serving from 1853-1870.
  This portrait was painted by Daniel Huntington in 1861.
- Howard Crosby, circa late 1800s; cuid18141; This portrait measures approximately 4' x 3'. (Item mc_376_cuid18141)
  Howard Crosby was the fourth Chancellor of NYU, serving from 1870-1881.
- John Hall, 1893; cuid18142; This portrait measures apprxoimately 6' x 5'. (Item mc_376_cuid18142)
  John Hall was the fifth Chancellor of NYU, serving from 1881-1891.
  This portrait was painted by Allan Jasper Conant in 1893.
- Henry Mitchell MacCracken, 1894; cuid18143; This portrait measures approximately 5' x 4'. (Item mc_376_cuid18143)
  Henry Mitchell MacCracken was the sixth Chancellor of NYU, serving from 1891-1910. His son, John Henry MacCracken, filled in for part of a year before Brown took over the office.
  This portrait was painted by Alfred M. Turner in 1894.
- Elmer Ellsworth Brown, early 1900s; cuid18144; This portrait measures approximately 57.7" x 47.5" x 3.75". (Item mc_376_cuid18144)
  Elmer Ellsworth Brown was the seventh Chancellor of NYU, serving from 1911-1933.
  This portrait was painted by George R. Boynton in the early 20th century.
- Harry Woodburn Chase, 1948; cuid18145; This portrait measures approximately 10' x 5'. (Item mc_376_cuid18145)
  Harry Woodburn Chase was the eighth Chancellor of NYU, serving from 1933-1951.
  This portrait was painted by DeWitt M. Lockman in 1948.
- Henry Townley Heald, 1962; cuid18146; This portrait measures approximately 30" x 26". (Item mc_376_cuid18146)
  Henry Townley Heald was the ninth Chancellor of NYU, serving from 1952-1956.
  This portrait was painted by Erik Haupt in 1962.
- Carroll Vincent Newsom, 1962; cuid18147; This portrait measures approximately 30" x 26". (Item mc_376_cuid18147)
  Carroll Vincent Newsom was the 10th Chancellor of NYU, serving from 1956-1962.
- James McNaughton Hester, 1975; cuid18148; This portrait measures approximately 4.5' x 3.5'. (Item mc_376_cuid18148)
  James McNaughton Hester was the 11th President of NYU, serving from 1962-1975. He was the first chief administrator at NYU to be called President.
  This portrait was painted by Aaron Shikler in 1975.
- John C. Sawhill, 1986; cuid18149; This portrait measures approximately 4' x 3'. (Item mc_376_cuid18149)
  John C. Sawhill was the 12th President of NYU, serving from 1975-1980.
  This portrait was painted by Everett Ray Kinstler in 1986.
- John Brademas, 1992; cuid18150; This portrait measures approximately 64.25" x 64.25" x 3". (Item mc_376_cuid18150)
  John Brademas was the 13th President of NYU, serving from 1981-1991.
  This portrait was painted by Hernán Cortés Moreno in 1992.
- L. Jay Oliva, 2002; cuid18151; This portrait measures approximately 64.25" x 64.25" x 3". (Item mc_376_cuid18151)
  L. Jay Oliva was the 14th President of NYU, serving from 1991-2002.
  This portrait was painted by John Howard Sanden in 2002.
- John Sexton, 2015; cuid18152; This portrait measures approximately 66.5" x 54.5" x 2.75". (Item mc_376_cuid18152)
  John Sexton was the 15th President of NYU, serving from 2003-2015.
  This portrait was painted by Daniel Mark Duffy in 2015.
- Andrew D. Hamilton, 2023; cuid18153; This portrait measures approximately 48" x 68". (Item mc_376_cuid18153)
  Andrew D. Hamilton was the 16th President of NYU, serving from 2016-2023.
  This portrait was painted by Jamie Lee McMahan in 2023.